<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Grandsire graybeard. Or Machiauell displayed</title>
            <title>Uncasing of Machivils instructions to his sonne. Abridgments</title>
            <author>Breton, Nicholas, 1545?-1626?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1635</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16803</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3704.9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110244</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845832</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845832</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10758</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16803)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10758)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1180:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Grandsire graybeard. Or Machiauell displayed</title>
                  <title>Uncasing of Machivils instructions to his sonne. Abridgments</title>
                  <author>Breton, Nicholas, 1545?-1626?</author>
                  <author>M. P. (Martin Parker), d. 1656?, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by William Stansby] for Richard Higgenbotham, and are to bee sold in the bulwarke neere the Tower at the signe of the Vnicorne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1635.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An abridgment, with additions, of: Breton, Nicholas. The uncasing of Machivils instructions to his sonne.</note>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to Martin Parker, who may have made the revisions.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>With a title-page woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B (-A1).</note>
                  <note>In two parts, each with separate dated title page.</note>
                  <note>Only known copy has a fake title page, on which this description is based.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 19241 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of a photostat of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1900.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10758:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10758:1"/>
                  <p>GRANDSIRE GRAYBEARD. OR Machiauell Diſplayed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Wits Wiſdome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Wit</hi> ſaith that this for <hi>Wiſdome</hi> goes</l>
                     <l>(Oh pitie!) <hi>Virtus poſt nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>s.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
                  <figure/>
                  <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Richard Higgenbotham,</hi> and are to bee ſold in the Bulwarke neere the Tower at the ſigne of the Vnicorne 1635.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10758:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10758:2"/>
                  <head>TO THE READER, (with the Contents) a CAVEAT.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>OLd grand-ſire <hi>Gray-beard,</hi> who the world had tride<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>And (by experience) learn'd both good, &amp; bad;</l>
                     <l>Tendring his Sonne, thought good (before he dide,)</l>
                     <l>To leſſon well his beſt beloued lad:</l>
                     <l>Leſt he ſhould fall by following the World,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe tricks he tels and how they be controld.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>COnceiue <hi>Wits Wiſdome</hi> with conſentleſſe heart,</l>
                     <l>He that hath eares to heare, <hi>here</hi> ſtop them faſt,</l>
                     <l>Peruſing it, vſe wiſe <hi>Vlyſſes</hi> Art,</l>
                     <l>And manacle thy minde to <hi>Vertues</hi> Maſt:</l>
                     <l>Be like the <hi>Bee,</hi> ſucke out the ſweet and good,</l>
                     <l>The ranke refuſe, let be the <hi>Spiders</hi> food.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10758:3"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10758:3"/>
                  <head>Grandſire Graybeard.</head>
                  <div type="preface">
                     <head>The Preface.</head>
                     <l>COme hither Son, and learne thy fathers lore,</l>
                     <l>It is not now as it hath beene of yore:</l>
                     <l>For in my youth would no man read to me,</l>
                     <l>That now (in age) I can deliuer thee.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>Precept 1.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>IF thou wilt be a man of much eſteeme,</l>
                        <l>Be not the ſame what euer ſo thou ſeeme.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="2">
                        <l>Speake faire to all, be courteous, gentle, kiad,</l>
                        <l>But let the world know nothing of thy minde.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="3">
                        <l>Let ſlip no time, may be for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>uai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e,</l>
                        <l>But truſt no friend for <hi>Faith</hi> beginnes to faile,</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="4">
                        <l>Refuſe no gifts to fill thy coffers full,</l>
                        <l>The wiſeſt poore man paſſeth for a Gull.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="5">
                        <l>Be temperate in affect, no quarrels moue,</l>
                        <l>And if thou loue thy ſelfe, f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ll not in loue.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:10758:4"/>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="6">
                        <l>Haue care for all men, but confer with few,</l>
                        <l>And count faire words to be but as a dew.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="7">
                        <l>Follow the time, finde humors, flatter pride,</l>
                        <l>And praiſe the <hi>Groom,</hi> but only pleaſe the <hi>Bride.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="8">
                        <l>Str<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ue not with great ones, meddle not with ſmall,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>or trifles trouble not thy ſelfe at all.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="9">
                        <l>Frequent the <hi>Church,</hi> make ſhew of great deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</l>
                        <l>And be not baſhfull to receiue promotion.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="10">
                        <l>Looke big at beggers, weare thy cloathes neat,</l>
                        <l>And ſpen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> not to much money at thy meat.</l>
                        <l>Saue thy horſe-meat at thy couzins ſtable,</l>
                        <l>And take thy trencher at anothers table.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="11">
                        <l>Breake ieſts on cowards, but take heede of knaues,</l>
                        <l>And loue no bawds for they are beaſtly ſlaues.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="12">
                        <l>Be perfect in <hi>Arithmeticks</hi> cloſe Art,</l>
                        <l>In all accompts to make a ſauing part.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="13">
                        <l>Obſerue the Lyon, doe not ſtirre the Beare,</l>
                        <l>And loue the Woolfe but only for the haire.</l>
                        <l>Learne of the Aſſe to beare, the Dogge to wait.</l>
                        <l>And of the Ape to counterfet conceit.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="14">
                        <l>Catch not at flies, they are but ſwallowes food,</l>
                        <l>But loue the meat that nouriſheth the blood.</l>
                        <l>Feed like a Woolfe on blood whilſt it is warme.</l>
                        <l>He is a foole that feeles anothers harme.</l>
                        <l>Yet ſcome as kinde as he that ſeemes to crie,</l>
                        <l>To ſee him ſicke, whom he would wiſh to die.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Take heed of intereſt, ſell nor gage no land,</l>
                        <l>And from aſſurance euer keepe thy hand.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Take no mans word, for coine is hard to get,</l>
                        <l>And t'is a cuſtome (now) to pay no debt.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:10758:4"/>
                        <l>Stand not to looke vpon a Peacocks taile,</l>
                        <l>Who (if he ſee his leggs) will ſtoope his ſailer</l>
                        <l>When <hi>Iack-Dawes</hi> chatter, let the language go,</l>
                        <l>Better be ſilent then to prattle ſo.</l>
                        <l>Come not within the verdict of a Iury,</l>
                        <l>And come not neare a Tyrant in his fury:</l>
                        <l>Commit no ſecrets to thy ſecond Selfe,</l>
                        <l>For neuer yet was Ape but plaid the Elfe.</l>
                        <l>Kill not a flie, and let a flea alone,</l>
                        <l>That ſucks the blood, and neuer hurts the bone.</l>
                        <l>File not thy finger's with a filthy Slut,</l>
                        <l>And ride not often on a gauld-backt cut.</l>
                        <l>Feare not a ſhadow, but auoid a danger,</l>
                        <l>And doe not keepe a Iade at rack and manger,</l>
                        <l>Remember nothing that thou doeſt not write,</l>
                        <l>Leſt danger doe thy fearefull heart affright.</l>
                        <l>Be ſociable in each company,</l>
                        <l>But haue no hand in any villany.</l>
                        <l>Be conuerſant with ſtrangers, learne languages,</l>
                        <l>Sound their eſtate, marke their carriages,</l>
                        <l>Know their diuerſities of wares, their worths and priſes,</l>
                        <l>But trouble not thy ſelfe with vain deuices.</l>
                        <l>Learn to know kingdoms, nations &amp; their natures</l>
                        <l>Their lawes their iudgements male &amp; female crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures;</l>
                        <l>And how their wealth doth riſe, by war or peace,</l>
                        <l>And how their ſtates begin, and how they ceaſe;</l>
                        <l>How they may be offended or defended,</l>
                        <l>And how their quarrels grow and which way en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</l>
                        <l>But of all <hi>Notes,</hi> note chiefely this of all,</l>
                        <l>How thou maiſt riſe, who euer hap to fall.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:10758:5"/>
                        <l>Suſpect thy wit, be wary of thy will,</l>
                        <l>And learne to ſpare, but neuer learne to ſpill.</l>
                        <l>Thinke no man wiſe but he that gathers wealth,</l>
                        <l>And keepe the diet that preſerues thy health.</l>
                        <l>Sit not vp late, vnleſſe it be for gaine,</l>
                        <l>For lack of ſleepe is hurtfull for the braine.</l>
                        <l>Goe not to Sea, whilſt thou maiſt liue on land,</l>
                        <l>Leſt ſcaping rockes thou fall vpon the Sand.</l>
                        <l>Trauell with eaſe, take beed of taking cold,</l>
                        <l>And (next to God) take comfort in thy gold.</l>
                        <l>Get all contentment that the world can giue,</l>
                        <l>For (after death) who knoweth how we liue?</l>
                        <l>Strange things are ſpoken, but beleeue the beſt,</l>
                        <l>And leaue the worſt. I leaue thee to the reſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="17">
                        <l>Promiſe enough, but not performe too much:</l>
                        <l>Yet with thy betters euermore keepe touch.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="18">
                        <l>Weare not thy ſhooes too ſhort, nor cloake too long</l>
                        <l>Vſe thy friends well, but doe thy ſelfe no wrong.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="19">
                        <l>Abandon foo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>es, make much of cunning wits,</l>
                        <l>But fauour moſt that moſt thy profit fits.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="20">
                        <l>Worke all the weeke for profit euery way,</l>
                        <l>And keepe thy <hi>Conſcience</hi> for the Holy day.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="21">
                        <l>Firſt if thou be a <hi>Courtier,</hi> know thy place,</l>
                        <l>And doe not ſerue for only ſhew of grace;</l>
                        <l>But let thy profit anſwerthy expence,</l>
                        <l>Leſt want do proue a wofull patience,</l>
                        <l>And thou doe proue the prouerbe often told,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>A careleſſe Courtier</hi> young, a begger old.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="22">
                        <l>And if thou beeſt a Scholler and canſt preach</l>
                        <l>And knoweſt rightly how thy flocke to teach;</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:10758:5"/>
                        <l>Let neuer conſcience at thy profit knocke,</l>
                        <l>But ſheare thy ſheepe, and fleece anothers flockes</l>
                        <l>For be thou poore what ere thy preaching be,</l>
                        <l>Thy pariſh will not paſſe a pin for thee.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="23">
                        <l>If that thou be a <hi>Souldier,</hi> ſerue for fame</l>
                        <l>But let thy golden pay maintaine the ſame;</l>
                        <l>For he that ſpends more then he gets in ſight,</l>
                        <l>Will be a begger, though he be a knight.</l>
                        <l>And if thou be a <hi>Lawyer,</hi> know the right,</l>
                        <l>But keepe thy client in a cunning plight.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="24">
                        <l>For how canſt thou a cunning pleading hold,</l>
                        <l>If that thy tongue be not well tipt with gold?</l>
                        <l>And rich attir'd, thou ſhalt haue roome to ſtand,</l>
                        <l>And plead thy cauſe whatere thou haſt in hand.</l>
                        <l>But barely clad, and in a poore array,</l>
                        <l>Thou maiſt (perhaps) haue hearing at dooms-day:</l>
                        <l>For though the Law be right and iudge be iuſt,</l>
                        <l>Yet with the rich the begger may not thruſt.</l>
                        <l>If that thou be a <hi>Merchant</hi> marke thy trade,</l>
                        <l>And of thy wares what reckning will be made<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="25">
                        <l>And be not lauiſh in a lewd expence,</l>
                        <l>Leſt banqu'rout proue a bad experience.</l>
                        <l>And if thou be a crafts man weigh thy paines,</l>
                        <l>And let no Alehouſe eat out all thy gaines;</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>For if thy charge aboue thy getting goe</l>
                        <l>Thou wilt be quickly in the beggers Roe.</l>
                        <l>What ſaith the crafty clowne in clowted ſhooes?</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Time</hi> was ordain'd to get, and not to looſe.</l>
                        <l>What though the poore lie ſtaruing in the ditch?</l>
                        <l>It is the dearth of corne makes farmers rich.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:10758:6"/>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="27">
                        <l>Aime ſtill at profit howſoere it growes,</l>
                        <l>Make the wind ſerue thee whereſoere it blowes,</l>
                        <l>For tis this <hi>wealth,</hi> this <hi>profit,</hi> and this <hi>gaine,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>That dies the coulour euer more in graine.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="28">
                        <l>Learne the <hi>Phyſitian</hi> and the <hi>Lawyers</hi> fee,</l>
                        <l>And (for thy profit) ſpeake as faire as hee.</l>
                        <l>Promiſe the one good ſpeed, the other <hi>health,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>In any courſe tis good to gather <hi>wealth.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Learne all diſeaſes and their ſeuerall cures,</l>
                        <l>And care not what the patient heart endures;</l>
                        <l>But giue him one day griefe, another caſe,</l>
                        <l>Not as his patience but his purſe doth pleaſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="29">
                        <l>Learne Cards and Dice, and any cheating play</l>
                        <l>That may bring in thy profit any way.</l>
                        <l>Learne how to ſtop a Card and cogge a Die,</l>
                        <l>But ſhift it cleanely from the Gameſters eye:</l>
                        <l>At Ruffe and Trumpe note how the dealer rubs,</l>
                        <l>There is no packe without the Knaue of clubs.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="30">
                        <l>Learne all Religions, be of eu'ry Sect,</l>
                        <l>And (chiefely) to thy profit haue reſpect.</l>
                        <l>For this ſame (<hi>conſcience</hi>) is ſo bare a thing,</l>
                        <l>As it will make a begger of a King.</l>
                        <l>Learne to get riches by the beggers purſe,</l>
                        <l>The Fox fares beſt when geeſe begin to curſe.</l>
                        <l>Learne eu'ry trade and traffique, traine and tricke,</l>
                        <l>And liue not by the dead but by the quicke.</l>
                        <l>In ſumme, of what eſtate ſoere thou be,</l>
                        <l>Learne to be rich, for that will hold with thee;</l>
                        <l>Be rich I ſay my Boy, be rich and wiſe,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Gold</hi> is a precious mettall for the eyes.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:10758:6"/>
                        <l>Why? rich men (they) haue money and gay geere,</l>
                        <l>And goodly houſes, and moſt dainty cheefe:</l>
                        <l>Faire wiues, fine pictures, plaies &amp; courtly dances</l>
                        <l>And many cheats that come by many chances:</l>
                        <l>Braue Siuer boxes, ſweet perfumes and waters,</l>
                        <l>And twenty other moe ſuch kinde of matters.</l>
                        <l>Whiles the poor man that pines for want offriends</l>
                        <l>May ſit and ſigh and picke his fingers ends.</l>
                        <l>And eu'ry morning waſh his face with teares,</l>
                        <l>And wipe his blubbred eyes with ſheu'led heares;</l>
                        <l>And walke abroad for forrowes recreation,</l>
                        <l>Or ſtarue himſelfe, or feed on contemplation.</l>
                        <l>Make curtſie to the ſhadow of a Lord.</l>
                        <l>And glad to get a looke, and halfe a word;</l>
                        <l>Bluſh and fal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> back when gay folke come in place,</l>
                        <l>And ſtart to looke a Lady in the face.</l>
                        <l>Talke to the aire where no man liſts to heare him,</l>
                        <l>And plod alone, where no man will come neer him.</l>
                        <l>And thus recording of a heauy care,</l>
                        <l>He feeds (perhaps) vpon a hungry fare;</l>
                        <l>Till ſome good Knight or learned Gentleman,</l>
                        <l>(That is a prudent Polititian</l>
                        <l>And can make vſes of afflicted braines,</l>
                        <l>And gather profit from their toiling paines)</l>
                        <l>May hap to grace him with a countenance,</l>
                        <l>Giue him a blew coat with a cognizance,</l>
                        <l>An old caſt doublet, or a paire of boots,</l>
                        <l>Feed him with brown bread, ſmal beere, hearbs &amp; roots</l>
                        <l>And now and then (perhaps) a peece of meat,</l>
                        <l>That ſcarce a man would giue a dogg to eat;</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:10758:7"/>
                        <l>Or after (haply) ſome good ſeruice done,</l>
                        <l>Make him a Tutor to his youngeſt Sonne.</l>
                        <l>Laugh at thoſe beggers, ſpeake in ſcorne at pelſe</l>
                        <l>Care thou for nothing but t'enrich thy ſelfe.</l>
                        <l>For <hi>Truth</hi> reports that doth of thrift intreat,</l>
                        <l>If thou be rich thou quickly writ be great.</l>
                        <l>Plot for a pudding, or a peece of ſouſe,</l>
                        <l>The Cat would neuer watch (but for a Mouſe,)</l>
                        <l>The Fox would neuer hunt (but for his prey.)</l>
                        <l>And workmen (but for gaine) would play all day<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                        <l>It is this <hi>Wealth,</hi> this <hi>Profit,</hi> and this <hi>Gaine,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>That makes the Labourer ſing away his paine.</l>
                        <l>Set ſnares for Wod cocks, pit-falls for ſmall birds,</l>
                        <l>And catch a foole with nothing but faire words.</l>
                        <l>Dandle the Child, grow inward with the Nurſe,</l>
                        <l>And thinke no beggry baſe that fills the purſe.</l>
                        <l>Laugh with the Lecher at Maides baſh fulnes,</l>
                        <l>And with the Chaſte at fleſhly filthineſſe,</l>
                        <l>And with the ſpend-thrift at the miſers buggs,</l>
                        <l>And with the Miſer at the beggers raggs.</l>
                        <l>Diſſ wade no Princes from their choice of pleaſure,</l>
                        <l>Nor a rich Miſer from his loue of treaſure.</l>
                        <l>If he be rich, what euer ſo he be,</l>
                        <l>Seeme in thy humour to be iuſt as he.</l>
                        <l>If he be poore, then let him beg alone,</l>
                        <l>It is a trade that few grow rich vpon.</l>
                        <l>Perſwade a ſlaue he is a gentleman,</l>
                        <l>Although he drop out of a dripping pan:</l>
                        <l>It is no matter, if his purſe can beare it;</l>
                        <l>His raſcall pride wih neuer bluſh to heare it.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:10758:7"/>
                        <l>Perſwade a Clowne, that he is halfe a Knight,</l>
                        <l>And that his wealth deſerues that place aright,</l>
                        <l>And his <hi>Maid-Marian</hi> with her winſcot face,</l>
                        <l>Might be a Lady (but for licke of grace.)</l>
                        <l>And make her thinke that ſhe is halfe a Queene,</l>
                        <l>And ſcarce on earth is ſuch another ſeene,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>For vertue, beauty, wit, for ſhape and feature:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Though God (he) knowes, that ſhe is no ſuch crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</l>
                        <l>But if ſhe doe applaud it, tis no matter;</l>
                        <l>He is a foole (for profit) cannot flatter.</l>
                        <l>Commend a <hi>Souldier</hi> when he is in crownes,</l>
                        <l>And ſweare a Knight muſt gouerne ouer Clownes.</l>
                        <l>In many a campe how be his caske did beare,</l>
                        <l>Although (poore Coward!) he came neuer there:</l>
                        <l>But yet be ſure thy flattery ſo to frame</l>
                        <l>That thine may be the gaine, though his the fame.</l>
                        <l>Commend the Lawyer, and his ſtudious reading,</l>
                        <l>Admi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e his iudgement, and extoll his pleading<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>But flatter ſo, that if thou get a fee,</l>
                        <l>Thou mai'ſt haue out a ſhare as well as he.</l>
                        <l>Follow a <hi>Biſhop</hi> with a world of praiſe,</l>
                        <l>And make him as the Loadſtarre of thy dayes;</l>
                        <l>Admi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e him, and extoll him to the skies,</l>
                        <l>But ſo, that thou maiſt get a Benefice,</l>
                        <l>A Vicridge, Cure, a Clarkeſhip or ſome ſuch,</l>
                        <l>As will returne thee profit ſmall or much.</l>
                        <l>Commend the <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ant,</hi> honour his aduenture,</l>
                        <l>Who gets his wealth by danger, not Indenture;</l>
                        <l>Commend his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ade his craffique, and his truth,</l>
                        <l>The honor of his age, and toyle of youth;</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:10758:8"/>
                        <l>But yet (with all) be ſure to flatter ſo,</l>
                        <l>That to thy purſe ſome peece of money grow,</l>
                        <l>Or on his boord thy trencher may be laid,</l>
                        <l>Or borrowed money neuer to be paid,</l>
                        <l>And tell <hi>(What-lacke yee)</hi> that he lackes no wit,</l>
                        <l>And (for his head) that he deſerues to ſit</l>
                        <l>On higher ſeates then the Church-wardens ſtooles</l>
                        <l>For he hath more wit then a world of fooles.</l>
                        <l>But yet in feeding of his idle vaine,</l>
                        <l>Be ſure to pick-out ſome odd priuate gaine</l>
                        <l>A rapier, dagger, ſtockings, boots, or ſhoes,</l>
                        <l>Some-what doth well, though beggers may not choſe.</l>
                        <l>Tell <hi>Mistr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>s-minks</hi> (coy ſhe) that keepes the ſhop,</l>
                        <l>She is a Ship that beares a gallant top;</l>
                        <l>She is a Lady for her louely face,</l>
                        <l>And for her countenance halfe a Princeſſe grace;</l>
                        <l>Then bite the lippe and winke, and hang the head,</l>
                        <l>And giue a figh as if thy heart were dead.</l>
                        <l>And ſhew ſtrange paſſions of affections ſence,</l>
                        <l>That ſhe may pittie loue (Sr.) reuerence.</l>
                        <l>But let the iſſue of this comming be,</l>
                        <l>That from her purſe ſome profit come to thee.</l>
                        <l>A peece of ſattin, fuſtian, or ſome ſtuffe,</l>
                        <l>A falling band, or a three double-ruffe,</l>
                        <l>A hat, a ſhirt, a cloak-cloth, or a ring,</l>
                        <l>Kniues, purſes, gloues, or ſome ſuch pretty thing,</l>
                        <l>For (ſomewhat hath ſome ſauour) t'is this gaine,</l>
                        <l>That to muention giues the ſweeteſt vaine.</l>
                        <l>Why? tell a <hi>Cobler</hi> he is halfe a King,</l>
                        <l>When ore his patches he can ſit and ſing,</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:10758:8"/>
                        <l>And knocke his Laſt, and whet his cutting knife,</l>
                        <l>There is no kingdome to a merry life.</l>
                        <l>But yet in telling of this idle tale,</l>
                        <l>Be ſure (at leaſt) to get a pot of ale.</l>
                        <l>For this ſame <hi>(nothing)</hi> brings no world about,</l>
                        <l>Better play ſmall games then be cleane ſhut out.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="31">
                        <l>If that thy Wife be faire, and thou be poore,</l>
                        <l>Let her ſtand like a picture at thy doore,</l>
                        <l>Where (though ſhe doe put picke her fingers ends)</l>
                        <l>Faire eies, fond looks will gaine a world of friends,</l>
                        <l>Play at <hi>bo-peepe,</hi> ſee me, and ſee me not,</l>
                        <l>It comes off well that is ſo cloſely got.</l>
                        <l>And euermore (ſay I) well fare the vent,</l>
                        <l>That paies the charges of the houſe and rent.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="32">
                        <l>If that thy Wife be old, thy daughter young,</l>
                        <l>And faire of face, or of a fluent tongue;</l>
                        <l>If by her Sutours ſiluer may be had,</l>
                        <l>Beare with ſmall faults, the good wil help the bad.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="33">
                        <l>If thy Maid-ſeruants be kind hearted wenches,</l>
                        <l>And cloſely make kinde bargains on thy benches,</l>
                        <l>If by their pleaſure may thy profit grow,</l>
                        <l>Winke at a wanton; who hath not beene ſo?</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="34">
                        <l>If that thy friend doe lacke a little wit,</l>
                        <l>And in his humor haue an idle fit,</l>
                        <l>To take a Wife, and vſe thee for his wooing,</l>
                        <l>Speake for thy friend, but for thy ſelfe be doing,</l>
                        <l>For euery friend is to his friend a debter,</l>
                        <l>To loue him as himſelfe, (but yet no better.)</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="35">
                        <l>But for thy ſelfe if thou haſt got a Wife,</l>
                        <l>Make ſhew to loue her dearely (as thy life)</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:10758:9"/>
                        <l>Though (for thy quiet) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>hou couldſt be content,</l>
                        <l>A <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> charge were at her buriall ſpent.</l>
                        <l>An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>hat (charge) be of thy griefe he ground,</l>
                        <l>For many Wiues are better loſt then found.</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> come vnto the ſecond matching,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> for feare of cunny catching,</l>
                        <l>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> to twenty wenche, in a day,</l>
                        <l>But let no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ſid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>es lead thy heart away.</l>
                        <l>But where thou find'ſt good ſtore of land, or gold,</l>
                        <l>There lay in cloſe to purchaſe a tree-hold.</l>
                        <l>And be not ſqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>miſh at a nice conceit,</l>
                        <l>That may diſſwade thee from a pleaſing bait.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="36">
                        <l>If thou be rich and ha'ſt anothers pride,</l>
                        <l>(That he may goe on foote while thou doſt ride)</l>
                        <l>Finde meanes to feede his ſwelling humor ſo,</l>
                        <l>That high conceit may aboue compaſſe go,</l>
                        <l>Till <hi>Fortunes</hi> frownes his folly ſo do checke,</l>
                        <l>That male<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> content do after breake his necke;</l>
                        <l>Then lay in for his lands, his goods, his place,</l>
                        <l>But ſtill bee ſure to keepe thy ſelfe in grace.</l>
                        <l>But if thou be not vp, and ſeek'ſt to riſe,</l>
                        <l>Step by degrees, and in thy ſteps be wiſe.</l>
                        <l>Creepe, crouch, and kneele, vntill thou be aloft,</l>
                        <l>But then ſit faſt, for feare, thou fall not ſoft.</l>
                        <l>Refuſe no ſeruice, be it nere ſo baſe,</l>
                        <l>By any meanes may bring thee into grace.</l>
                        <l>And make no conſcience to attend on ſin,</l>
                        <l>To keepe the doore where Diuels dance within.</l>
                        <l>Find a rich Heire, and note his diſpoſition,</l>
                        <l>How he is giu'n to baſeneſſe or ambition,</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:10758:9"/>
                        <l>And with thy lending lay his land aboord,</l>
                        <l>That he may be thy ſlaue and thou his Lord.</l>
                        <l>Who in the whole will vndermine ſo faſt,</l>
                        <l>Hee'le leaue his Lordſhip like the land of waſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="37">
                        <l>If that thou haſt a Partner in thy ſtocke,</l>
                        <l>And both your wealths lie all vnder one locke;</l>
                        <l>And if thy Partner ride abroade for pleaſure,</l>
                        <l>And put thy faith in truſt with all thy treaſure;</l>
                        <l>At his returne do vpon quarrels ſtand,</l>
                        <l>When thou haſt got his wealth into thy hand.</l>
                        <l>Say, in accounts he hath deceiued thee,</l>
                        <l>(Although thou knoweſt no ſuch matter be:)</l>
                        <l>When, if he will not take what thou wilt giue him</l>
                        <l>To courſe of law (for his beſt comfort) driue him:</l>
                        <l>Where, while he railes on thy ill conſcience,</l>
                        <l>Thy patience cloſely ſhall put vp his pence.</l>
                        <l>And whatſoeuer honeſt mindes ſurmiſe,</l>
                        <l>Wealth (with the wealthy) make the wealthy wiſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="38">
                        <l>Be rich therefore, I ſay, be rich my Sonne,</l>
                        <l>For wealth will ſway the world when all is done.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10758:10"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10758:10"/>
                  <p>GRANDSIRE GRAYBEARD. OR Machiauell Diſplayed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Wits Wiſdome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Wiſdome <hi>'gainſt</hi> Wit <hi>replieth thus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Virtutib. aurum vilius.</l>
                  </q>
                  <figure/>
                  <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Richard Higg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>am,</hi> and are to bee ſold in the Bulwa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke neere the Tower at the ſigne of the Vnicorne 1635</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10758:11"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10758:11"/>
                  <head>TO THE READER A Tranſition.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>NOw hauing tane a view of villany,</l>
                     <l>Whereby thou maist <hi>Wits</hi> wicked wiles diſcern</l>
                     <l>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oſe wiſedome is vntruth and tyrannie,</l>
                     <l>More wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>leſome read heere <hi>(Reader)</hi> maiſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                           <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> learne:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Wits-Wiſedome,</hi> let it crue thy contemplation,</l>
                     <l>But <hi>Wiſedoms-Wit,</hi> thy life and conuerſation.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The world (it) aimes at wealth pompe, &amp; delight,</l>
                     <l>And him it doth account for wittie wiſe;</l>
                     <l>Who hath the craft, the cunning, and the ſleight,</l>
                     <l>By my plot to mount and to ariſe:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Plaine-dealing</hi> loe, dies begger, that's the worſt,</l>
                     <l>But <hi>Fraude</hi> foreuer dies with ſhame accurſt.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10758:12"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10758:12"/>
                  <head>Grandſire Graybeard.</head>
                  <div type="preface">
                     <head>The Preface.</head>
                     <l>BVt now my ſon, that thou haſt learnd this lore,</l>
                     <l>(Vpon my bleſſing) looke on it no more</l>
                     <l>Except it be (by ill) to know the good;</l>
                     <l>But yet take heed leſt it be vnderſtood.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>Precept 1.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>BE that thou ſeem'ſt to be, in word and deed,</l>
                        <l>Leſt <hi>Pater n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ſter</hi> put thee from his <hi>Creed.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="2">
                        <l>Faire ſpeech is good, but keep not a foule mind,</l>
                        <l>For hollow hearts are of a helliſh kinde.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="3">
                        <l>A good beginning makes a bleſſed end,</l>
                        <l>And hold him for a dogge that hath no friend.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="4">
                        <l>Receiue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> bribe to fill a ruſtie cheſt,</l>
                        <l>A quiet conſcience is a Kingly feaſt.</l>
                        <l>And tis a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>eauie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ence in ſorrowes Roule,</l>
                        <l>To ſaue the body and to looſe the Soule.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:10758:13"/>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="5">
                        <l>In <hi>Honors</hi> cauſe, maintaine thy reputation,</l>
                        <l>And hold loue good for Reaſons recreation.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Affect the wiſe and with the learned talke,</l>
                        <l>And with the vertuous often make a walke.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="7">
                        <l>Sooth no ill cares with idle flatterie,</l>
                        <l>Honour the Bride, but doe the Groome no Rie,</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="8">
                        <l>With great or ſmall be ſure to keep eu'n meaſure,</l>
                        <l>And ſcorne no trifle that may doe thee pleaſure.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="9">
                        <l>Frequent the <hi>Church,</hi> with faith &amp; true deuotion,</l>
                        <l>And doe not ſtep too faſt vnto promotion.</l>
                        <l>For farre more griefe is in a headlong fall,</l>
                        <l>Than if thy care had neuer climbd at all.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="10">
                        <l>Be wiſely kinde to eu'ry quality,</l>
                        <l>And euer keepe good hoſpitality.</l>
                        <l>At thine owne charge keepe thy horſes ſtable,</l>
                        <l>And ſeeke no banquet at a beggers table.</l>
                        <l>For a true minde had rather ſtarue then eat,</l>
                        <l>When churles or ſeruants grudge a ſtranger meat.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="11">
                        <l>Ieſt not with cowards, for they will but cry,</l>
                        <l>And as for bawds, pitie their beggery.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="12">
                        <l>
                           <hi>Arithmeticke</hi> is ſeene in eu'ry trade,</l>
                        <l>But true accompts are euer to be made.</l>
                        <l>For when the laſt count-reckning is caſt vp,</l>
                        <l>Then ſhall the crafty take their poiſoned cup.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="13">
                        <l>For Lions, Beares, For Wolues, for Apes &amp; Aſſes</l>
                        <l>Leaue them to figure humours looking-glaſſes.</l>
                        <l>And haue a care to carry ſo thy ſelfe,</l>
                        <l>No ſtorme may driue thy ſhip vpon the ſhelfe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="14">
                        <l>Swallowes doe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>eed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>es, but light they ſlie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                        <l>While <hi>Epicures</hi> in too much feeding die.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:10758:13"/>
                        <l>By others harms ſeeke not thy priuate good,</l>
                        <l>A bloody feaſt is an vntimely food.</l>
                        <l>And to diſſemble loue is ſuch an euill,</l>
                        <l>As neereſt ſhewes the nature of the Deuill.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="15">
                        <l>To helpe thy friends, do not forbeare thy hand,</l>
                        <l>And (for thy credit) ſell both goods and land.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="16">
                        <l>Denie no friend, when he doth friendly craue it,</l>
                        <l>For honeſt minds will pay, when as they haue it,</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="17">
                        <l>Performe thy word, but promiſe not too much,</l>
                        <l>With rich and poore be carefull to keepe touch.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="18">
                        <l>Let garments fit thy body, grace thy minde,</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="19">
                        <l>And to thy friend (as to thy ſelfe) be kinde.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="20">
                        <l>Let care of <hi>conſcience,</hi> guide thre eu'ry way,</l>
                        <l>To giue thee comfort on the holy day.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="21">
                        <l>Firſt if thou be a <hi>Courtier</hi> know the grace,</l>
                        <l>And ſeeke in heau'n to haue a higher place,</l>
                        <l>And if on earth ſuch ſeruice profit brings,</l>
                        <l>What ſhall he haue that ſerues the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Kings?</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="22">
                        <l>If that thou be a <hi>Scholler</hi> and canſt preach,</l>
                        <l>With ſimple truth thy ſimple Audience teach;</l>
                        <l>And feed thy flocke thou haſt in charge to keepe.</l>
                        <l>Leſt that thou proue a Wolfe vnto thy ſheepe,</l>
                        <l>But whatſoeuer (here) be thine eſtate,</l>
                        <l>There is none poore but hee whom God doth hate.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="23">
                        <l>And if thou be a <hi>Souldier,</hi> ſucke no blood,</l>
                        <l>To Kingly minds it is vnchriſtian food.</l>
                        <l>And honours title who doth truly hold,</l>
                        <l>Shall it in mercy finde, and not in gold.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="24">
                        <l>If that thou be a <hi>Lawyer,</hi> iudge the right,</l>
                        <l>And let no briberie bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nde a bleſſed ſight:</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:10758:14"/>
                        <l>For thou ſhalt finde it writ in Mercies roule,</l>
                        <l>Better a thread bare gown, than thred-bare ſoule</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="25">
                        <l>And if thou be a <hi>Merchant,</hi> know thy cares,</l>
                        <l>And do not wound thy conſcience with thy wares</l>
                        <l>Leſt in repentance all too late thou finde,</l>
                        <l>The gaine is loſſe that feeds a greedy minde.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="26">
                        <l>In briefe, of what eſtate ſoere thou bee,</l>
                        <l>Let truth and conſcience euer gouerne thee.</l>
                        <l>Let clownes clap all their craft on clowted ſhoes,</l>
                        <l>Seeke thou no earthly gaine thy Heau'n to looſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="27">
                        <l>Aime at no profit with a poiſoned breath,</l>
                        <l>Leſt it be paied in thy ſecond death.</l>
                        <l>An honeſt gaine in eu'ry trade doth well,</l>
                        <l>The winde blowes ill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>hat blowes the ſoule to hell.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="28">
                        <l>In <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Phyſicke</hi> haue a conſcience,</l>
                        <l>In making gaine of thy experience.</l>
                        <l>Leſt that thy Clients crie, or patients death,</l>
                        <l>Make thee cry out and howle in hel beneath.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="29">
                        <l>For <hi>Cards</hi> and <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ce</hi> and all ſuch idle play,</l>
                        <l>From thy delight diſcard and caſt away.</l>
                        <l>For deale or rub whoſe hap it be to haue,</l>
                        <l>The Knaue of <hi>Clubs</hi> will euer be a Knaue.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="30">
                        <l>By wicked plots do neuer prole for pelfe,</l>
                        <l>Let thy <hi>Soules</hi> care be neereſt to thy ſelfe.</l>
                        <l>And ſooth no humours in an euill minde,</l>
                        <l>For poiſning breath is of a helliſh kinde.</l>
                        <l>And though to hurt a few to help a many</l>
                        <l>Seeme good, yet (better) not the helpe of any.</l>
                        <l>Flatte no Miſtris <hi>Fubs,</hi> or <hi>Iohn<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </hi> a <hi>Noddes,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Nor honour golden Calues, nor wodden gods.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:10758:14"/>
                        <l>Nor puffe a Peaſant vp with flattering pride,</l>
                        <l>A raſcall will but like a Begger ride.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="31">
                        <l>If that thy wife be faire, be thou not foule,</l>
                        <l>To let her play the Ape, and thou the Owle.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="32">
                        <l>And to thy daughter be a better Sire,</l>
                        <l>Then l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ke a hackney let her out to hire.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="33">
                        <l>And for thy ſeruants let no belly ſwell,</l>
                        <l>A baudy-houſe is but an earthly hell.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="34">
                        <l>Be faithful to thy Wife, firme to thy friend,</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="35">
                        <l>And conſtant in religion to the end.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="36">
                        <l>If thou be rich, abandon wicked pride,</l>
                        <l>And doe not on the horſe of enuie ride,</l>
                        <l>Nor ſeeke the well deſeruing to diſgrace,</l>
                        <l>Nor put the vertuous ſpirit out of place.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="37">
                        <l>If that thy friend doe truſt thee with his loue,</l>
                        <l>Vnto his truſt do not a Traitor proue;</l>
                        <l>Leſt he that ſeeth thy ill-gotten treaſure,</l>
                        <l>Do pay thee home with an il-meaten meaſure,</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="38">
                        <l>Be rich and wiſe in that good wit, my Boy,</l>
                        <l>That death nor hell, nor deuill can deſtroy.</l>
                        <l>Tax no mans name in any euill matter,</l>
                        <l>But like a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> deale with euery creature.</l>
                        <l>Be ſorry for the euill thou haſt done,</l>
                        <l>And go on with the good thou haſt begunne.</l>
                        <l>Pray for thy faith, that it may faile thee neuer,</l>
                        <l>So (though thou die) yet ſhalt thou liue for euer.</l>
                        <l>Serue GOD, thy King, be to thy Country true,</l>
                        <l>Liue till thou die, then bid the world adue.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
